Guide to the Americans For Immigrant Justice Records, 1982-2020; 1982-ongoing and undated RL.00035
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Audiovisual Materials, 1989-2013; 49 items audio and video cassettes
  - With Liberty and Justice for All?, 2001 (Box 44, Video-cassette RL00035-VHS-0012)
  - Women and Children, Florida Immigrant Advocacy Center, YAP Inc., 2001 (Box 44, Video-cassette RL00035-VHS-0028)
  - Freedom! A National of Immigrants, FIAC, 2002 (Box 44, Video-cassette RL00035-VHS-0014)
  - Would You Harbor Me? Florida Immigrant Advocacy Center, Ynot Art Productions, Inc., 2003 (Box 44, Video-cassette RL00035-VHS-0031)
  - Interview with Dr. José Pedro Greer, 2003-04-23 (Box 97, Video-cassette RL00035-VHS-0002)
  - Angels of Justice, Y Not Productions, FIAC, 2004 (Box 44, Video-cassette RL00035-VHS-0010)
  - Interview, FIAC, 2004-11 (Box 44, Video-cassette RL00035-VHS-0013)
  - Sweet Land of Liberty, Florida Immigrant Advocacy Center, 2005 (Box 44, Video-cassette RL00035-VHS-0033)
  - Securing Our Borders, Post 9/11 Scapegoating of Immigrants, Prepared by Cheryl Little and Kathie Klarreich, FIAC, 2005-04 (Box 97, Video-disc RL00035-DVD-0004)
  - US Senator Bob Graham and FIAC, 2006 (Box 97, Video-cassette RL00035-VHS-0004)
  - Tenth Anniversary, Florida Immigrant Advocacy Center, 2006 (Box 44, Video-cassette RL00035-VHS-0011)
  - Tenth Anniversary, Florida Immigrant Advocacy Center, 2006 (Box 97, Video-disc RL00035-DVD-0004)
  - Palm Bay City Council Meeting, 2006-08-03 (Box 97, Video-cassette RL00035-VHS-0003)
    Also see "Anti-Immigrant city ordinances in Florida" in the Subject Files series.
  - Cuban EAD case press conference- photos, FIAC, 2006-09-07 (Box 97, Video-disc RL00035-DVD-R-0002)
  - Mayan kids Day 1 interview, 2000s (Box 97, Audio-disc RL00035-CD-R-0001)
  - Sove Nou, promo, Kijik Multimedia, 2000s (Box 97, Video-disc RL00035-DVD-0003)
  - 16 Years Defending the American Dream. AIJ, 2012 (Box 97, Video-disc RL00035-DVD-0001)
  - Deportee, Chantal Regnault and Rachele Magloire, 2012 (Box 97, Video-disc RL00035-DVD-R-0001)
  - Dare to Dream 17th Anniversary. AIJ, 2013 (Box 97, Video-disc RL00035-DVD-0002)
- Photographic Materials Series, 1989-1995, and undated, 2 boxes
  Series includes photos of Guantanamo 1994-1995, Krome 1989-1990, demonstrations and other miscellaneous photos, in black and white and in color, undated.
  - Assorted 1989-1995 and undated (Box 45)
    Includes photos of Guantanamo 1994-1995, Krome 1989-1990, demonstrations and other miscellaneous photos, undated.
  - Guantanamo advocates, 1991-1992 (Box 45)
  - Miscellaneous extras of camp scenes, 1994 (Box 45)
  - Guantanamo detainee statement trip, 1995 May, 5 folders (Box 45)
    Florida Immigrant Advocacy Center trip to take statements from children and adult Haitians detained at Guantanamo camps.
  - Guantanamo L.A., 1995 (Box 45)
  - Guantanamo Camp #9, 1990-1995 (Box 45)
  - Guantanamo Camp #9 kids, 1994-1995 (Box 45)
  - Guantanamo press conference Homestead AFB, 1995 (Box 45)
  - Guantanamo, various, 1994-1995 (Box 45)
    Family Camps 4, 5, 7; Cuban paintings; Camp #11; goodbye party, views of camps.
  - Karla's Visit to Haiti, Guantanamo, 1995 Aug., 2 folders (Box 45)
    Repatriation of Haitian unaccompanied minors.
  - Haiti, 1995 Aug. 6-13 (Box 45)
  - Ship Arauole - SMII, undated and 1995 (Box 45)
    Photos were taken sometime between 1991-1996. These photos are related to the Ismae Lawsuit. The boat is docked with 3 Haitian stow-aways held in a cage on the docks. Also contains photos of a plane to Guantanamo in 1995.
  - FLS and other events, office photos, undated (Box 45)
  - Haitian Refugee Center, undated, 1-7 of 14 folders (Box 45)
    Cheryl Little with Haitian Refugee Center, Inauguration of Aristide.
  - Haitian Refugee Center, undated, 8-14 of 14 folders (Box 46)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 46)
    Primarily staff on-site.
- Subject Files Series, 1993-2017
  Series contains AIJ's research and advocacy files on diverse immigration issues such as immigration related legislation, detention and asylum, DACA and Dreamers, law enforcement, human trafficking, scams and exploitation of immigrants. Documents include research files, correspondence, studies, testimony, press and media, educational materials, and FOIA documents.
  - 2300 bed facility in FL, 2011-2012 (Box 54)
  - Abuses in INS custody, 1998 (Box 54)
  - Action plan for AIJ, 2013 (Box 54)
  - Adams Violence Against Women Act Bill, 2008-2012 (Box 54)
  - American Bar Association site visits, 2004 (Box 80)
  - Amici curiae briefs filed, 2013-2016 (Box 80)
  - Anti-Immigrant city ordinances in Florida, 2006 (Box 56)
    Advocacy and research documents related to a series of proposed city ordinances promoted by anti-immigrant groups. The ordinances aimed to target employers of undocumented immigrants. Files related primarily to the proposed ordinances in Palm Bay, FL and Avon Park, FL. Also see video, "Palm Bay City Council Meeting," RL00035-VHS-0003, in the Audiovisual Materials series.
  - Anti-Prop 187 advocacy, 1991-1996 (Box 75)
    Includes meeting minutes, memos, correspondence, newspaper clippings, agendas, questionares, opposition research, and other documents on efforts against Prop 187 type legislation or referendums in the state of Florida that sought to block access to medical care and education for undocumented immigrants. There are a number of documents related to Citizens for Florida, the coalition formed to oppose Proposition 187 in FL.
  - Articles about children in detention, 2009 (Box 54)
  - Baby Margaret case, 2000 (Box 54)
    The case of "Baby Margaret", an 18 month old infant brought from Jamaica to the US, stateless and unidentifed, later deported once her identity was confirmed. The case serves as an example of the need for legal representation for unaccompanied minors.
  - Baker county jail case FOIA and other records, 2009-2014 (Box 84)
  - Bivens action for child asylum seekers, 2002 (Box 54)
  - Board meeting on legal work, May 17 2017 (Box 80)
  - Bonds for detainees, 1998-2000 (Box 54)
  - BTC report source info, 2002-2013 (Box 81)
  - Centers for American Progress senior fellow files, 2009 (Box 54)
  - Citizens for Florida contacts, 1996 (Box 54)
  - CLEAR Act, 2003-2004 (Box 58)
    Documents containing information on opposition to the proposed CLEAR Act that would authorize and incentivize local police forces to detain undocumented immigrants and seize their assets.
  - Coast Guard meeting, April 2013 (Box 54)
  - Coerced waivers of legal rights, 2007 (Box 54)
  - Communities report, 2011 (Box 80)
  - Conditions in detention facilities, 2013 (Box 54)
  - Correspondence with congressional representatives, 2015-2016 (Box 54)
  - Costs and benefits of immigration, 2011-2012 (Box 81)
  - Criminal prosecution of asylum seekers, 2003-2005 (Box 54)
  - Cuban and Haitian policies, 2006 (Box 80)
  - Custom and Border Patrol (CBP) documents, 2011-2016 (Box 54)
  - Custom and Border Patrol (CBP) hieleras, 2008-2013 (Box 54)
  - Custom and Border Patrol (CBP) hieleras FOIA, 2013-2015 (Box 84)
  - Custom and Border Patrol (CBP) lawsuit, 2008-2016 (Box 58)
  - Congressional report on unaccompanied children, 2007 (Box 54)
  - Dale v USA, 2005-2011 (Box 58)
    A Jamaican detainee suing for abuses he suffered while in detention in Louisiana.
  - Detained minors, 2012 (Box 81)
    Folder named Kids in detention.
  - Detention articles and reports, 2007-2014 (Box 54)
  - Detention of asylum seekers from the Middle East, 2001 (Box 54)
  - Detention center condition questionnaire, early 2000s (Box 54)
  - Detention conditions, 2015 (Box 54)
  - Detention conditions, 2010-2011 (Box 81)
  - Detention dehumanizing, 2009-2011 (Box 81)
  - Detention logs litigation, 2014 (Box 54)
  - DHS and CBP letters, 2003-2013 (Box 54)
  - Dreamers and DACA documents (Box 57)
    Contains documents related to the DREAM Act, DACA recipients, advocacy and legislation affecting DACA recipients aka Dreamers.
  - Dreamers Gomez brothers coverage, 2007-2008 (Box 80)
  - Electronic monitoring device, 2003-2004 (Box 58)
  - Endgame detention and removal strategic plan, 2003-2012 (Box 80)
  - Enforcement policy and issues, 2011-2012 (Box 81)
  - Enforcing immigration law reports, 2001-2005 (Box 58)
  - Expedited removal, 1997-2002 (Box 57)
  - Family separation, 2011-2012 (Box 81)
  - Federal detainer procedures, 2014 (Box 54)
  - FIAC and CCLS Amici Curiae, 2000 (Box 80)
  - FIAC requests for meetings with police departments, 2004 (Box 80)
  - Florida Department of Law Enforcement (FDLE) meeting, 2003 (Box 54)
  - Florida statistics, 2009 (Box 54)
  - FOIA requests, 1998-2013 (Box 54)
  - Fort Pierce, FL police correspondence, 2006 (Box 54)
  - Forum with Miami police chief John Timoney, 2006 (Box 54)
  - General information on class action lawsuits, 1990s (Box 54)
  - Grants for LUCHA and Nou Kab programs, 2009-2011 (Box 54)
  - Habeas Corpus, 1993-2000 (Box 58)
  - Haitian and Cuban disparities, 2010-2017 (Box 58)
  - Hate crimes, 2006-2011 (Box 81)
  - Hospital deportees, 2003 (Box 54)
  - Human trafficking and modern slavery articles, 1997-2011 (Box 54)
  - ICE FOIA case, 2010-2011 (Box 58)
  - ICLASP grant application, 2010 (Box 54)
  - ICLASP info, 2009 (Box 54)
  - IJ misconduct, 2007-2013 (Box 54)
  - Immigration enforcement research, 2001-2014 (Box 54)
  - Immigration judges, 2002-2008 (Box 54)
  - Immigration reform, 2000 (Box 58)
  - Immigration reform, 2009-2012 (Box 54)
  - Immigrant ID scams, 2000-2017 (Box 58)
  - Inconsistent and inhumane policies, 2011-2012 (Box 81)
  - Indefinite detention, 1999-2003 (Box 80)
  - INS communications, 1998-2000 (Box 54)
  - INS ineptitude and inefficiencies with visa processing, computers, 2001-2002 (Box 58)
  - INS v Enrico St. Cyr, March 27 2001 (Box 80)
  - Inter-American Commission on Human Rights visit to US detention centers, 2009 (Box 54)
  - Jennie Santos FOIA, 2015 (Box 99)
  - Know Your Rights enforcement, 2002-2004 (Box 81)
  - LA testimony, December 13, 2006 (Box 58)
  - Lawyers for legal literacy, 2005 (Box 80)
  - LeaDawn Ferguson v USA et al files, 2013-2016 (Box 84)
    The case of a US citizen detained and sedated against her will under the suspicion of being an migrant drug mule due to her recent travels to the Dominican Republic. Medical procedures were performed on her against her will and she was not informed that she had been sedated, the aftereffects of which caused her to be involved in a car accident on her way back home.
  - Legal immigrants targeted, 2010-2011 (Box 81)
  - Letter to John Morton, December 14, 2010 (Box 58)
  - Letter to Secretary of Labor Solis, 2010 (Box 58)
  - LGBT related and other cases, 2015 (Box 58)
  - Local police, 2006 (Box 58)
  - McCain Kennedy bill, 2005 (Box 58)
  - Medical care for detainees, 2010-2012 (Box 81)
  - Meeting with ICE HQ, January 29, 2014 (Box 58)
  - Miami airport questions, 1996 (Box 54)
  - Miami-Dade Bill of Rights defense committee draft resolution, October 15 2003 (Box 81)
  - Miami-Dade police correspondence, 2006-2009 (Box 54)
  - Miami-Dade police public records request, 2007 (Box 54)
  - Miscalleanous FOIA requests, 2004-2009 (Box 84)
    FOIA requests submitted by AIJ related to various cases such as conditions in a Monroe County Jail detention center in Key West, FL, Haitian TPS status, Krome riots, and guidelines for the release of Florida public records.
  - Morris Dee Award, 2000-2006 (Box 54)
  - Newsletters and articles, 2000-2010 (Box 58)
  - Old Key bridges and Cubans, 2006 (Box 80)
  - Operation Liberty Shield, 2003 (Box 58)
    Opposition to the DHS policy ordering the mandatory detention of asylum seekers from over 34 countries.
  - Operation Tarmac, 2003 (Box 58)
    Information on raids conducted against Florida airport workers that were allegedly using false documents.
  - Opinions on indefinite detention with Homeland Security, 2001 (Box 58)
  - Oscar documentary, 2014 (Box 54)
  - Panel on immigration issues at CG Congregational Church, November 1, 2016 (Box 58)
  - Pamphlets and information on asylum and voluntary removal, 2001-2002 (Box 54)
  - Pamphlet in English on voluntary departure, early 2000s (Box 54)
  - Pamphlet in Spanish on asylum, early 2000s (Box 54)
  - Photo print outs of Krome hunger strike and AIJ staff and volunteers, 2000s (Box 54)
  - Post Trump election, 2016-2017 (Box 58)
  - Prop 187 advocacy, 1996 (Box 58)
  - Prosecution of asylum seekers, 2003-2005 (Box 57)
  - Prosecutorial discretion, 2011-2014 (Box 58)
  - Public records request from South Florida police departments pursuing day laborers, 2003-2007 (Box 54)
  - Recommendations for detention centers, 2001 (Box 81)
  - Research for op-ed on detention, 1999-2007 (Box 54)
  - Sanctuary cities in Miami-Dade County, 2017 (Box 58)
  - Scams, 2007-2009 (Box 58)
  - Secure communities, 2009-2010 (Box 81)
  - Secure Communities program, 2009 (Box 54)
    Secure Communities was a program allowing law enforcement and ICE to collaborate using biometric and other identifying technology to locate and aprehend criminal aliens and deport them.
  - Secure Communities update, 2013-2015 (Box 58)
  - Sexual assault and domestic violence, 2007-2011 (Box 81)
  - SIJ visas article, 2008 (Box 54)
  - SIJ visas flow charts, 2008 (Box 54)
  - Southwest ranches FLS Community Justice Project, 2008-2012 (Box 58)
  - Special registration, 2003 (Box 58)
  - Statistics of arrival of UACs at SW border, 2014 (Box 58)
  - Surge of UM arrivals, 2014-2015 (Box 58)
  - Town hall meeting on America two years after 9/11, September 10 2003 (Box 80)
  - TPS FOIAs, 2009 (Box 81)
  - Transitioning INS to DHS, 2003 (Box 58)
  - Trumps executive orders John Kelly's memos, 2017 (Box 58)
  - TVPRA Act, 2009 (Box 54)
  - Unaccompanied children, 2004-2016 (Box 58)
  - Unaccompanied minors crisis, 2014 (Box 54)
  - Unaccompanied minors data, 2008-2009 (Box 54)
  - Unaccompanied minors footnotes, 2009 (Box 54)
  - Undocumented immigrants eligible for admission to the Florida Bar, 2011 (Box 58)
  - US citizens detained, 2008 (Box 99)
    Notes on US citizens unlawfully detained due to racial profiling and assumptions they are undocumented. Includes the case of a US citizen of Mexican descent born in the US to US born parents.
  - Various FOIA requests, 2003-2004 (Box 60)
  - Vera Institute statistics, 2009 (Box 54)
  - WeCount! Inc. et al v DHS, March 3, 2012 (Box 58)